<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A tract concerning schism and schismaticks wherein is briefly discovered the original causes of all schism / by the ever-memorable Mr. John Hales ...</title>
            <author>Hales, John, 1584-1656.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1700</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 32 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A44486</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H279</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R174</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13648558</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13648558</idno>
            <idno type="VID">100961</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A44486)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 100961)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 789:18)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A tract concerning schism and schismaticks wherein is briefly discovered the original causes of all schism / by the ever-memorable Mr. John Hales ...</title>
                  <author>Hales, John, 1584-1656.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1700.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Schism --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Heresy --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:100961:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:100961:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A TRACT CONCERNING SCHISM AND <hi>Schiſmaticks:</hi> Wherein is briefly Diſcovered The <hi>Original Cauſes</hi> of all <hi>Schiſm.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By the Ever-memorable Mr. <hi>JOHN HALES,</hi> Of <hi>Eaton College,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed in the Year MDCC.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:100961:2"/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:100961:2"/>
            <head>A Tract concerning <hi>Schiſm.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>HEreſie</hi> and <hi>Schiſm,</hi> as they are common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly uſed, are two Theological Scare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crows, with which they who uſe to up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold a Party in Religion, uſe to fright away ſuch, as making Inquiry into it, are ready to relinquiſh and oppoſe it, if it appear either erro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neous and ſuſpicious; for, as <hi>Plutarch</hi> reports of a Painter, who having unskilfully painted a Cock, chaſed away all Cocks and Hens, that ſo the Imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of his Art might not appear by Compariſon with Nature; ſo Men willing for Ends to admit of no Fancy but their own, endeavour to hinder an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiry into it by way of Compariſon with ſomewhat with it, peradventure truer, that ſo the Deformity of their own might not appear: But howſoever, in the common Manage, <hi>Hereſie</hi> and <hi>Schiſm</hi> are but ridiculous Terms, yet the Things in themſelves are of very conſiderable Moment; the one offending againſt Truth, the other againſt Charity, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore both deadly, when they are not by Imputation, but indeed.</p>
            <p>It is then a Matter of no ſmall Importance, truly to deſcry the Nature of them, and they on the contrary ſtrengthen themſelves, who through the Iniquity of Men and Times are injuriouſly charged with them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Schiſm</hi> (for of <hi>Hereſie</hi> we ſhall not now treat, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept it be by Accident, and that by occaſion of a general Miſtake, ſpread through all the Writings of the Ancients, in which their Names are familiarly confounded:) <hi>Schiſm,</hi> I ſay, upon the very Sound of the Word, imports Diviſion; <hi>Diviſion</hi> is not but where <hi>Communion</hi> is or ought to be: Now <hi>Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion</hi> is the Strength and Ground of all Society, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:100961:3"/>
               <hi>Sacred</hi> or <hi>Civil;</hi> whoſoever therefore they be that offend againſt the common Society and Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs of Men, if it be in Civil Occaſions, are guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Sedition and Rebellion: If it be by reaſon of <hi>Eccleſiaſtical</hi> Difference, they are guilty of <hi>Schiſm.</hi> So that <hi>Schiſm</hi> is an <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Sedition,</hi> as <hi>Sedition</hi> is a <hi>Lay Schiſm:</hi> Yet the great Benefits of <hi>Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion,</hi> notwithſtanding in regard of divers Diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers Men are ſubject to, Diſſention and Diſunion, are often neceſſary: For when either falſe or uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Concluſions are obtruded for Truth, and Acts either unlawful, or miniſtring juſt Scruple, are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired of us to be perform'd, in theſe Caſes, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent were Conſpiracy; and open Conteſtation is not Faction or <hi>Schiſm,</hi> but due Chriſtian Animoſity.</p>
            <p>For the opening therefore of the Nature of <hi>Schiſm,</hi> ſomething may be added by way of Difference to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh it from neceſſary Separation; and that is, that the Cauſe upon which Diviſion is attempted, proceed not from Paſſion or from Diſtemper, or from Ambition or Avarice, or ſuch other Ends, as Humane Folly is apt to purſue, but from well weighed and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary Reaſons, and that when all other Means having been tried, nothing will ſerve to ſave us from guilt of Conſcience, but open Separation; ſo that <hi>Schiſm,</hi> if we would define it, is nothing elſe but an unneceſſary Separation of Chriſtians from that part of the viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Church of which they were once Members. Now, As in Mutinies and Civil Diſſentions there are two Attendants in Ordinary belonging unto them; one the Choice of one Elector or Guide, in place of the general or ordinary Governor, to rule and guide; the other the appointing of ſome publick Place or Ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dezvous, where publick Meetings muſt be celebra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: So in Church-diſſentions and Quarrels, two Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>purtenances there are, which ſerve to make <hi>Schiſm</hi> compleat.
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:100961:3"/>
Firſt, in the Choice of a Biſhop, in oppoſition to the former, (a thing very frequent amongſt the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cients, and which many times was the Cauſe and Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect of <hi>Schiſm.)</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, The erecting of a new Church and Orato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, for the dividing parts to meet in publickly. For till this be done, the <hi>Schiſm</hi> is but yet in the Womb.</p>
            <p>In that late famous Controverſie in <hi>Holland, De Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtinatione &amp; auxiliis,</hi> as long as the diſagreeing Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties went no farther than Diſputes and Pen-combats, the <hi>Schiſm</hi> was all that while unhatch'd; but as ſoon as one Party ſwept an old Cloyſter, and by a pretty Art ſuddenly made it a Church, by putting a now Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit in it, for the ſeparating Party there to meet; now what before was a Controverſie became a formal <hi>Schiſm.</hi> To know no more than this, if you take it to be true, had been enough to direct you how you are to judge, and what to think of <hi>Schiſm</hi> and <hi>Schiſmaticks;</hi> yet, becauſe of the <hi>Ancients,</hi> (by whom many are more af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frighted than hurt) much is ſaid, and many fearful Dooms pronounced in this Caſe. We will deſcend a little to conſider of <hi>Schiſm,</hi> as it were by way of Story, and that partly farther to open that which we have ſaid in General, by inſtancing in Particulars, and partly to diſabuſe thoſe who reverencing Antiquity more than needs, have ſuffer'd themſelves to be ſcar'd with Imputation of <hi>Schiſm</hi> above due meaſure; for, what the <hi>Ancients</hi> ſpake by way of Cenſure of <hi>Schiſm</hi> in General, is moſt true; for they ſaw (and it is no great matter to ſee ſo much) that unadviſed and open Fancy to break the Knot of Union betwixt Man and Man, (eſpecially amongſt Chriſtians, upon whom, above all other kind of Men, the Tye of Love and Communion doth moſt eſpecially reſt) was a Crime hardly par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donable, and that nothing abſolves Men from the Guilt of it, but true and unpretended Conſcience: Yet when they came to pronounce of <hi>Schiſm</hi> in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular, (whether it was becauſe of their own Intereſt,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:100961:4"/>
or that they ſaw not the Truth, or for what other cauſe God only doth know) their Judgments many times (to ſpeak moſt gently) were juſtly to be ſuſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted. Which that you may ſee, we will range all <hi>Schiſm</hi> into two Ranks.</p>
            <p>Firſt is a <hi>Schiſm,</hi> in which only one Party is the <hi>Schiſmatick;</hi> for where Cauſe of <hi>Schiſm</hi> is neceſſary, there not he that ſeparates, but he that is the cauſe of ſeparation, is the <hi>Schiſmatick.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, There is a <hi>Schiſm</hi> in which both Parties are the <hi>Schiſmaticks;</hi> for, where the occaſion of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration is unneceſſary, neither ſide can be excuſed from the Guilt of <hi>Schiſm.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But you will ask, Who ſhall be the Judge, what is neceſſary? Indeed, it is a Queſtion which hath been often made, but I think ſcarcely ever truly anſwered, not becauſe it is a Point of great depth and difficulty truly to aſſoil it, but becauſe the true Solution of it carries ſire in the tail of it (for it bringeth with it a piece of Doctrine which is ſeldom pleaſing to Supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riors:) to you for the preſent this ſhall ſuffice.</p>
            <p>If ſo be you be <hi>anima defaecato,</hi> if you have cleared your ſelf from Froath and Growns, if neither Sloth, nor Fear, nor Ambition, nor any tempting Spirit of that nature abuſe you (for theſe and ſuch as theſe are the true Impediments, why both that, and other Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions of the like danger are not truly anſwer'd) if all this be, and yet you know not how to frame your Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution, and ſettle your ſelf for that doubt; I will ſay no more of you than was ſaid of <hi>Papias,</hi> St. <hi>John</hi>'s own Scholar, Your Abilities are not ſo good as I preſumed.</p>
            <p>But to go on with what I intended, and from that that diverted me, that you may the better judge of the nature of <hi>Schiſms</hi> by their occaſions, you ſhall find that all <hi>Schiſms</hi> have crept into the Church by one of theſe three ways, either upon matter of Fact, or upon matter of Opinion, or point of Ambition; for the firſt, I call that matter of Fact, when ſomething is
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:100961:4"/>
required to be done by us, which either we know, or ſtrongly ſuſpect to be unlawful. So the firſt nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <hi>Schiſm,</hi> of which we read in the Church, contain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in it matter of Fact; for, it being upon Error taken for neceſſary, that an <hi>Eaſter</hi> muſt be kept, and upon worſe than Error, (if I may ſo ſpeak) for it was no leſs than a Point of <hi>Judaiſm</hi> forced up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Church; upon worſe than Error, I ſay, thought farther neceſſary that the Ground of the Time for keeping of that Feaſt muſt be the Rule left by <hi>Moſes</hi> to the <hi>Jews,</hi> there aroſe a ſtout Queſtion, Whether we were to celebrate with the <hi>Jews</hi> on the fourteenth <hi>Moon,</hi> or the <hi>Sunday</hi> following? This mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter tho' moſt unneceſſary, moſt vain, yet cauſed as great a Combuſtion as ever was in the Church; the <hi>Weſt</hi> ſeparating and refuſing Communion with the <hi>Eaſt,</hi> for many Years together. In this fantaſtical Hur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry I cannot ſee but all the World were <hi>Schiſmaticks,</hi> neither can any thing excuſe them from that Impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, excepting only this, that we charitably ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe that all Parties did what they did out of Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, a thing which befel them through the ignorance of their Guides, (for I will not ſay, through their Malice) and that through the juſt Judgment of God, becauſe through Sloth and blind Obedience Men ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amined not the things which they were taught, but, like Beaſts of Burthen, patiently couch'd down, and indifferently underwent whatſoever their Superiors laid upon them. By the way, by this we may plainly ſee the danger of our Appeal to Antiquity, for Reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in controverted Points of Faith, and how ſmall Relief we are to expect from thence; for, if the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion of the chiefeſt Guides and Directors of the Church did in a Point ſo trivial, ſo inconſiderable, ſo mainly fail them, as not to ſee the Truth in a Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, wherein it is the greateſt Marvel how they could avoid the Sight of it, Can we, without the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation of great Groſsneſs and Folly, think ſo poor-ſpirited Peaſons competent Judges of the Queſtions
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:100961:5"/>
now on foot betwixt the Churches. Pardon me, I know what Temptation drew that Note from me.</p>
            <p>The next <hi>Schiſm</hi> which had in it matter of Fact, is that of the <hi>Donatiſts,</hi> who were perſwaded (at leaſt pretended ſo) that it was unlawful to converſe or communicate in Holy Duties with Men ſtained in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny notorious Sin; for howſoever that <hi>Auſtin</hi> do ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifie only the <hi>Thurificati &amp; Traditores</hi> and <hi>Libellatioi,</hi> &amp;c. as if he ſeparated only from thoſe whom he found to be ſuch, yet by neceſſary proportion he muſt referr to all notorious Sinners. Upon this he taught, that in all Places, where Good and Bad were mix'd toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, there could be no Church by reaſon of Pollu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, co-operating away from Sinners, which blaſted righteous Perſons, which converſed with them, and made all unclean. On this Ground, ſeparating him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf from all that he liſt to ſuſpect, he gave out, that the Church was no where to be found but in him and his Aſſociates, as being the only Men among whom wicked Perſons found no Shelter, and by conſequence the only clean and unpolluted Company, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the only Church. Againſt this, St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> laid down this Concluſion, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitatem Eccleſiae per totum mundum diſperſae praeceptam non eſſe diſſerendam,</hi> which is indeed the whole Summ of that Father's Diſputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion againſt the <hi>Donatiſts.</hi> Now in one part of this Controverſie one thing is very remarkable: The Truth was there, where it was, by meer Chance, and might have been on either ſide, the reaſon brought by either Party notwithſtanding: For tho' it were <hi>de facto,</hi> falſe, that <hi>pars Donati</hi> ſhut up in <hi>Africk,</hi> was the only Orthodox Party, yet it might be true, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding any thing St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> brings to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fute it; and on the contrary, tho' it were <hi>de facto,</hi> true, that the Part of Chriſtians diſperſed over the whole Earth were Orthodox, yet it might have been falſe, notwithſtanding any thing St. <hi>Augustine</hi> brings to confirm it. For where, or amongſt whom, or how
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:100961:5"/>
many the Church ſhall be, or is, is a thing indifferent; it may be in any Number, more or leſs, it may be in any Place, Country or Nation, it may be in all, and, for ought I know, it may be in none, without the Prejudice to the Definition of a Church, or the Truth of the Goſpel, <hi>North</hi> or <hi>South;</hi> many or few; diſperſed in many Places, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fined to one: None of theſe do either prove or diſprove a Church.</p>
            <p>Now this <hi>Schiſm,</hi> and likewiſe that former, to a wiſe Man that well underſtands the Matter in Controverſie, may afford perchance Matter of Pity, to ſee Men ſo ſtrange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſtracted upon Fancy, but of doubt or trouble what to do, it can yield none; for tho' in this <hi>Schiſm</hi> the <hi>Donatiſt</hi> be the <hi>Schiſmatick,</hi> and in the former both Parties be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qually engaged in the <hi>Schiſm,</hi> yet you may ſafely upon your Occaſions communicate with either, if ſo be you flatter neither in their <hi>Schiſm:</hi> For why might it not be lawful to go to Church with the <hi>Donatiſt,</hi> or to celebrate <hi>Eaſter</hi> with the <hi>Quartodeciman,</hi> if occaſion ſo require, ſince nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Nature, nor Religion, nor Reaſon doth ſuggeſt any thing of moment to the contrary? For in all Publick Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings pretending Holineſs, ſo there be nothing done, but what true Devotion and Piety brook, why may I not be preſent in them, and uſe communion with them? Nay, what if thoſe, to whom the execution of the publick Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice is committed, do ſomething either unſeemly or ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>picious, or peradventure unlawful? what if the Garments they wear be cenſured, nay indeed be ſuſpicious? what if the Geſture or Adoration to be uſed to the Altars, as now we have learned to ſpeak? what if the <hi>Homiliſt</hi> have preached or delivered any Doctrine of the Truth, of which we are not well perſwaded? a thing which very often falls out; yet for all this we may not ſeparate, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept we be conſtrained perſonally to bear part in them our ſelves. The Prieſts under <hi>Ely</hi> had ſo ill demeaned themſelves about the daily Sacrifices, that the Scripture tells us, they made them to ſtink; yet the People refuſed not to come to the Tabernacle, nor to bring their Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice to the Prieſt: For in thoſe <hi>Schiſms</hi> which concern Fact, nothing can be a juſt cauſe of refuſing of Communion, but
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:100961:6"/>
only to require the execution of ſome unlawful or ſuſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted Act; for not only in Reaſon, but in Religion too, that Maxim admits of no Releaſe, <hi>Cautiſſimi cujuſque Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptum quod dubit as ne feceris.</hi> Long it was e're the Church fell upon <hi>Schiſm,</hi> upon this occaſion, tho' of late it had very many; for until the ſecond <hi>Council</hi> of <hi>Nice,</hi> in which irreconcilable Superſtition and Ignorance did conſpire, I ſay, until the Rout did ſet up Image-worſhip, there was not any remarkable <hi>Schiſm</hi> upon juſt occaſion of Fact; all the reſt of <hi>Schiſms</hi> of that kind were but Wantons, this was truly ſerious; in this the <hi>Schiſmatical</hi> Party was the Synod it ſelf, and ſuch as conſpired with it, for, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Uſe of Images in Sacrifices.</p>
            <p>Firſt, It is acknowledged by all that it is a thing un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neceſſary.</p>
            <p>Secondly, It is by moſt ſuſpected.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, It is by many held utterly unlawful. Can then the enjoining of ſuch a thing be ought elſe but a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe? or can the refuſal of Communion here be thought any other thing than Duty? Here, or upon the like oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to ſeparate, may peradventure bring perſonal trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble or danger; (againſt which it concerns any honeſt Man to have <hi>pectus Praeparatum;)</hi> farther harm it cannot do, ſo that in theſe Caſes you cannot be to ſeek what to think, or what you have to do.</p>
            <p>Come we then to conſider a little of the ſecond ſort of <hi>Schiſm,</hi> ariſing upon occaſion of variety of Opinion: It hath been the common Diſeaſe of Chriſtians from the beginning, not to content themſelves with that meaſure of Faith which God and Scriptures have expreſly affor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded us, but out of a vain Deſire to know more than is revealed, they have attempted to deviſe things, of which we have no Light, neither from Reaſon nor Revelation; neither have they reſted here, but upon Pretence of Church-authority (which is none,) or Tradition (which for the moſt part is but feigned,) they have peremptorily conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and conſidently impoſed upon others, a neceſſity of entertaining Concluſions of that Nature, and, to ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en themſelves, have broken out into Diviſions and Facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, oppoſing Man to Man, Synod to Synod, till the Peace
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:100961:6"/>
of the Church vaniſhed, without all poſſibility of Recal: Hence aroſe thoſe ancient and many Separations amongſt Chriſtians, occaſioned by <hi>Arianiſm, Eutichianiſm, Neſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rianiſm, Photinianiſm, Sabellianiſm,</hi> and many more, both ancient, and in our time; all which indeed are but Names of <hi>Schiſm:</hi> Howſoever, in the common Language of the Fathers, they were called <hi>Hereſies;</hi> for <hi>Hereſie</hi> is an Act of the Will, not of the Reaſon, and is indeed a Lye and not a Miſtake, elſe how could that of <hi>Austin</hi> go for true, <hi>Errare poſſum, Haereticus eſſe nolo:</hi> Indeed <hi>Manichaniſm, Valentinianiſm, Macedonianiſm, Mahometiſm,</hi> are truly and properly <hi>Hereſies:</hi> For we know that the Authors of them received them not, but invented them themſelves, and ſo knew what they taught to be a Lye; but can any Man avouch that <hi>Arius</hi> and <hi>Neſtorius,</hi> and others that taught erroneouſly concerning the Trinity, and the Perſon of our <hi>Saviour,</hi> did maliciouſly invent what they taught, and not rather fall upon it by error and miſtake? Till that be done, and upon good evidence, we will think no worſe of all Parties than needs we muſt, and take theſe Rents in the Church to be at the worſt but <hi>Schiſms,</hi> upon mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Opinion, In which caſe, what we are to do, is not a point of any great depth of underſtanding to diſcover, if ſo be diſtemper and partiality do not intervene: I do not ſee, that <hi>opinionum varietas &amp; opiniantium unitas,</hi> are <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or that Men of different Opinions in Chriſtian Religion may not hold Communion <hi>in Sacris,</hi> and both go to one Church. Why may I not go, if Occaſion require, to an <hi>Arian Church,</hi> ſo there be no <hi>Arianiſm</hi> expreſs'd in their Liturgy? and were Liturgies and Publick Forms of Service ſo framed, as that they admitted not of particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar and private Fancies, but contained only ſuch things, as in which all Chriſtians do agree, <hi>Schiſms</hi> on Opinion were utterly vaniſh'd: For conſider of all the Liturgies that are and ever have been, and remove from them what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever is Scandalous to any Party, and leave nothing but what all agree on, and the Evil ſhall be, that the Publick Service and Honour of God ſhall no ways ſuffer. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as to load our Publick Forms with the Private Fancies upon which we differ, is the moſt ſovereign way to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuate
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:100961:7"/>
               <hi>Schiſm</hi> unto the World's end; Prayer, Confeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Thankſgiving, Reading of Scriptures, Adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Sacraments in the plaineſt and the ſimpleſt man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, were Matter enough to furniſh out a ſufficient Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgy, tho' nothing either of Private Opinion, or of Church-Pomp, of Garments, or preſcribed Geſtures, of Imagery, of Muſick, of Matter concerning the Dead, of many Superfluities which creep into the Church, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Name of Order and Decency, did interpoſe it ſelf.</p>
            <p>To charge Churches and Liturgies with things unne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, was the firſt Beginning of all Superſtition, and when Scruple of Conſcience began to be made or preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, there <hi>Schiſm</hi> began to break in; if the ſpecial Guides and Fathers of the Church would be a little ſparing of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumbring Churches with Superfluities, or not over-rigid either in reviving obſolete Cuſtoms, or impoſing new, there would be far leſs Cauſe of <hi>Schiſm</hi> or <hi>Superſtition,</hi> and all the Inconvenience were likely to enſue would be but this, they ſhould in ſo doing yield a little to the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>becility of their Inferiors, a thing which St. <hi>Paul</hi> would never have refuſed to do; mean while, whereſoever falſe or ſuſpected Opinions are made a piece of Church-Liturgy, he that ſeparates is not the <hi>Schiſmatick,</hi> for it is alike unlawful to make profeſſion of known or ſuſpected falſhood, as to put in practiſe unlawful or ſuſpected actions.</p>
            <p>The Third thing I named for Matter of <hi>Schiſm</hi> was <hi>Ambition,</hi> I mean <hi>Epiſcopal Ambition,</hi> ſhewing it ſelf e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially in two Heads, one concerning Pluralities of <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops</hi> in divers Sees. <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> tells us, That Neceſſity cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth but ſmall Faults, but Avarice and Ambition were the Mother of great Crimes: <hi>Epiſcopal Ambition</hi> hath made this true, for no Occaſion hath produced more frequent, more continuous, more ſanguinous <hi>Schiſms</hi> than this hath done. The Sees of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> of <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioch,</hi> and above all of <hi>Rome,</hi> do abundantly ſhew thus much, and all Eccleſiaſtical Stories witneſs no leſs, of which the greateſt that conſiſts of factionating and tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>multuating of great and potent <hi>Biſhops.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Socrates</hi> apologizing for himſelf, that profeſſing to write an Eccleſiaſtical Story, he did oft times interlace
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:100961:7"/>
the Actions of ſecular Princes and other civil Buſineſs, tells us, that he did this to refreſh his Reader, who other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe were in danger to be cloy'd by reading ſo much of the Acts of unquiet and unruly Biſhops, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, in which, as a Man may ſay, they made Butter and Cheeſe one of another; for <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> (that I may ſhew you a caſt of my old Office, and open you a Myſtery in Grammar,) properly ſignifies to make Butter and Cheeſe, and becauſe theſe are not made without much agitation of the Milk, hence <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, by a borrowed and tranſmu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ſignification, ſignifies to do things with much agita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and tumult.</p>
            <p>But that I may a little conſider of the two Heads I but now ſpecified, the firſt I mentioned was the <hi>Prelacy of Biſhops</hi> in one See. For the general Practice of the Church, ſince the beginning at leaſt ſince the original of Epiſcopa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, as now it is, was never to admit at once more than one Biſhop in one See; and ſo far in this point have they been careful to preſerve Unity, that they would not have a Biſhop in his See to have two Cathedral Churches; which thing lately brought us a Book out of <hi>France, De Mono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>machia Epiſcoporum,</hi> written by occaſion of the Biſhops of <hi>Langres,</hi> who, I know not upon what Fancy, could not be content with one Cathedral Church in his Dioceſs, but would needs have two, which to the Author of that Work ſeems to be a kind of Spiritual Polygamy. It fell out amongſt the Ancients very often; ſometimes upon oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of difference in Opinions, ſometimes becauſe of thoſe who were intereſſed in the Choice of Biſhops; that two and ſometimes more were ſet up, and all Parties ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving to maintain their own Biſhop, made themſelves ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Churches, ſeveral Congregations, each refuſing to participate with others, and many times proceeding to mutual Excommunications. This is that which <hi>Cyprian</hi> calls <hi>Erigere Altare contra Altare:</hi> To this doth he im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute the Original of all Church-diſorders; and if you read him, you would think he thought no other Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tumult to be <hi>Schiſm</hi> but this. This perchance may plead ſome Excuſe; for, tho' in regard of Religion it ſelf, it matters not whether there be one or more Biſhops in one
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:100961:8"/>
Dioceſs; for <hi>Epiphanius</hi> reckoning up the Biſhops of <hi>Rome,</hi> makes <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Paul</hi> the firſt; and St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgeth for a time he ſate Fellow-Biſhop with his Prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſor, tho' he excuſed it, that he did ſo, being ignorant that the contrary had been decreed by the Council of <hi>Nice;</hi> yet it being a thing very convenient for the Peace of the Church to have it ſo, neither doth it any whit favour of their Miſdemeanor, their Puniſhment ſleeps not, who unneceſſarily and wantonly go about to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fringe it.</p>
            <p>But that other Head of <hi>Epiſcopal Ambition,</hi> concerning <hi>Supremacy of Biſhops</hi> in divers Sees, one claiming <hi>Supre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy</hi> over another, as it hath been from time to time, a great Treſpaſs againſt the Church's Peace, ſo it is now the final Ruine of it. The <hi>Eaſt</hi> and <hi>Weſt,</hi> through the Fury of the two prime Biſhops, being irremediably ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated without all Hope of Reconcilement. And beſides all this Miſchief, it is founded on a Vice contrary to all Chriſtian Humility, without which no Man ſhall ſee his Saviour; for they do but abuſe themſelves and others, that would perſwade us, that Biſhops by <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s Inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion have any Superiority over other Men farther than of Reverence, or that any Biſhop is Superior to another far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than poſitive Order, agreed upon amongſt Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, hath preſcribed; for we have believed him that hath told us, that in Jeſus Chriſt there is neither High nor Low, and that in giving Honour every Man ſhould be ready to prefer another before himſelf; which Saying cuts off all Claim certainly of Superiority, by Title of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity, except Men think that theſe things were ſpoken only to poor and private Men. Nature and Religion agree in this, that neither of them hath an hand in this Heraldry of <hi>Secundum ſub &amp; ſupra:</hi> All this comes from the Compoſition and Agreement of Men amongſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; wherefore this Abuſe of Chriſtianity, to make it Lacquey to Ambition, is a Vice for which I have no ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary Name of Ignomy, and an ordinary I will not give it, leſt you ſhould take ſo tranſcendent a Vice to be but trivial.</p>
            <p>Now concerning <hi>Schiſm</hi> ariſing upon theſe Heads, you
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:100961:8"/>
cannot be for Behaviour much to ſeek; for you may ſafely communicate with all Parties, as Occaſion ſhall call you, and the <hi>Schiſmaticks</hi> here are all thoſe who are Head of the Faction, together with thoſe who foment it; for private and indifferent Perſons they may be Specta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors of theſe Contentious as ſecurely in regard of any Peril of Conſcience, (for of Danger in Purſe or Perſon I keep no account,) as at a Cock-fight where Serpen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> fight, who cares who hath the better? The beſt Wiſh is, That both may periſh in the Fight.</p>
            <p>And for Conventicles, of the Nature of which we deſire to be informed, thus much in general evidently appears, That all Meetings, upon an unneceſſary Separa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion are to be ſo ſtiled; ſo that in ſenſe a Conventicle is nothing elſe but a Congregation of <hi>Schiſmaticks,</hi> yet Time hath taken leave ſometimes to fix this Name upon good and honeſt Meetings, and that perchance not alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether without good Reaſon; for without Publick Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious Meetings thus it fares: Firſt, It hath been at all Times confeſſed neceſſary, that God requires not only inward and private Devotion, when Men either in their Hearts and Cloſets, or within their private Walls, pray, praiſe, confeſs and acknowledge; but he farther requires all thoſe things to be done in Publick, by troops and ſhoales of Men, and from hence have proceeded pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Temples, Altars, Forms of Service, Appointed Times, and the like, which are required for open Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies, yet whilſt Men were truly Pious, all Meetings of Men for mutual Help of Piety and Devotion where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever and by whomſoever celebrated, were permitted, without Exception.</p>
            <p>But when it was eſpied that ill-affected Perſons abuſed Private Meetings, whether Religious or Civil, to evil Ends, Religiouſneſs to groſs Impiety, as appears in the <hi>Ethnick, Eluſinia,</hi> and <hi>Bacchanalia,</hi> and Chriſtian Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings under the Pagan Princes, when for fear they durſt not come together in open View, were charged with foul Imputations, as by the Report of Chriſtians them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves plainly appears, and civil Meetings, many times under Pretence of friendly and neighbourly Viſits, ſhel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:100961:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
treaſonable Attempts againſt Princes and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monweals.</p>
            <p>Hence both Church and State joined, and jointly gave Order for Forms, Times, Places of Publick Meetings, whether for Religious or Civil Ends. And all other Meetings whatſoever, beſides thoſe of which both Time and Place are limited, they cenſured for Routs and Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ots; and unlawful Aſſemblies in the State, and in the Church for Conventicles.</p>
            <p>So that it is not lawful, no not for Prayer, for Hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, for Conference, for any other Religious Office what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever, for People to aſſemble otherwiſe than by Publick Order is allowed; neither may we complain of this in Times of Corruption, for why ſhould Men deſire to do that ſuſpiciouſly in Private which warrantably may be performed in Publick.</p>
            <p>But in Times of manifeſt Corruptions and Perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, wherein Religious Aſſembling is dangerous, Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Meetings howſoever, beſides Publick Order, are not only Lawful, but they are of Neceſſity and Duty; elſe how ſhould we excuſe Meetings of Chriſtians for Publick Service in Time of Danger and Perſecutions, and of our ſelves in Queen <hi>Mary</hi>'s Days? And how will thoſe of the Roman Church amongſt us put off the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation of Conventicling, who are known amongſt us privately to aſſemble for Religious Exerciſes, againſt all Eſtabliſhed Order, both in State and Church? For in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed all Pious Aſſemblies, in Times of Perſecution and Corruptions, howſoever practiſed, are indeed or rather alone the lawful Congregations, and Publick Aſſemblies, tho' according to Form of Law, are indeed nothing elſe but Riots and Conventicles, if they be ſtained with Corruption and Superſtition.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
